<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tyth-gatherers, no gospel officers. Or, Certaine briefe observations concerning the institution and paying of tythes, whereby it appears that men were never compelled to the payment of them in the Old Testament, nor did ever practice it in the New: that the Gospel contributions were all voluntary accounted as a free gift, not a debt; the apostles themselves, not only choosing to labour with their owne hands, but requiring all their successours to doe the like, that they might not bee chargeable to any of their disciples. Together with some quotations out of Mr. Selden, a Member of the House of Commons, his History of Tythes, for the writing whereof he was much troubled by the Episcopall tythmongers of those times, from whom the Presbyterian church-publicans of these days, have learnt to persecute with far greater violence, all such as doe but speak against their Gospel-taxations, ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1307B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E319_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861269</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861269</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94380)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 52:E319[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tyth-gatherers, no gospel officers. Or, Certaine briefe observations concerning the institution and paying of tythes, whereby it appears that men were never compelled to the payment of them in the Old Testament, nor did ever practice it in the New: that the Gospel contributions were all voluntary accounted as a free gift, not a debt; the apostles themselves, not only choosing to labour with their owne hands, but requiring all their successours to doe the like, that they might not bee chargeable to any of their disciples. Together with some quotations out of Mr. Selden, a Member of the House of Commons, his History of Tythes, for the writing whereof he was much troubled by the Episcopall tythmongers of those times, from whom the Presbyterian church-publicans of these days, have learnt to persecute with far greater violence, all such as doe but speak against their Gospel-taxations, ...</title>
                  <author>Selden, John, 1584-1654. Historie of tithes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 22, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the hopefull-yeare both of civill and Christian liberty, 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan 27 London 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Selden, John, 1584-1654. --  Historie of tithes.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113400:1"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis little Pamphlet would not have needed a preparatory Epiſtle, were there not amongſt us a very great generation who are parties in the point I ſpeak of; I ſhall therefore crave leave to propound unto them, before they read it, whether the Clergy-bellies of theſe times can bee any whit better Chriſtians, than <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver-Smith with his Craftſmen, <hi>Act</hi> 19 19.20. &amp;c. whilſt they cry out, <hi>Great is the God of tithes! Sacred is the duty of tithes! of tythes we fill, and ſwill, hold belly, hold; were it not for tythes lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning would be neglected, the Miniſtery deſpiſed, and wee muſt take paines like other ſilly people of the Laity: Let us rather cram the Priſons full, as wee doe our guts with tythe pigs, of all ſuch as ſacrilegiouſly refuſe to pay us tythes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me likewiſe intreat them to conſider, whether it were not the ſame Tyth-ſpirit, the ſpirit of covetouſneſſe, which cauſed the Maſters of the Damſell, out of whom <hi>Paul</hi> caſt the evill ſpirit, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. &amp;c. not only to hang backe from receiving the Goſpell, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to perſecute the Apoſtles for cutting off that Diveliſh gaine which the evill ſpirit had wont to bring them? Let them interrogate their owne conſciences, whether they believe it to bee Scripture or good doctrine, that <hi>a gift blindeth the wiſe, and perverteth the words of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> Ex. 23.8. Deut. 16.19. that it <hi>deſtroyeth the heart,</hi> Eccleſiaſtes 20.29. corrupting their very underſtandings, in ſuch manner, that they even perſwade themſelves to be in the right, when they were never more in the wrong: Let ſuch, I ſay, who alwayes had, and ſtill have the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of their ſoules imprinted with this <hi>gift</hi> or rather <hi>theft of tithes,</hi> conſider and ſuſpect themſelves to be no competent Judges, how much this Goſpel-tithing ſavors of <hi>Judaiſme, Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> and is inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the ſubjects prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y.</p>
            <p>Being thus prepared, I ſhall deſire them with mee to obſerve, that the Levites being excluded from poſſeſſing any inheritance in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> unleſſe the Lord had given them his owne portion and inheritance the tythes, Deut. 18 1.2. they muſt have ſtarved, and yet we finde not that the Lord gave them any compulſive power for levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bringing in this contribution of tythes: But under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb facs="tcp:113400:2"/>where the whole land is open and free to all alike, to Clergy as well as to Laity, to purchaſe and keep poſſeſſion of, where the Apoſtles practice was to labour with their owne hands, 1 Theſſ. 2.9. and <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſſe command to all in generall, that if any would not worke hee ſhould not eat, 2 Theſſ. 3.10. for a ſuppoſititious illegitimate tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> who are not above the five hundreth part of the Kingdom (there being upon calculation thought to be not above one Clergyman to every 500. men and women) to lay claime to, and by violence poſſeſſe themſelves of the tythes of all encreaſe, free of all charges, which in valuation is better then if the fifth part of the whole land were divided amongſt them for gleab-land, whereof moſt of them have ſome ſmall pittance beſides their tythes, is the greateſt cheat and robbery which was ever practiſed; I ſay yet more briefly, that if the whole Kingdome were to bee divided into 500. parts, the Clergy (as I ſaid before, being but as one to 500. by computation) beſides the free denization which they enjoy in common withall other people, run away with about one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty five ſhares, I mean with about one hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty five times as much as any of their fellows; Oh prodigy of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe! but I muſt decipher it more cleerly.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe there were 500. men and women in a Country Pariſh, and all the land in that Pariſh to be worth 2000 l. by the yeare; the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who is but one of the aforeſaid 500. pretends 200 l. for his tithes of the aboveſaid 2000 l. cleer of all charges, which ſaid charges on all arrable grounds one with another, for manuring, ſeed-corne and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, &amp;c. or of ſtocking paſture ground, together with the hazard of a ſmall crop, or death of cattell, is ſo great, as that the land-lords to bee free of paying tythes, the tenth ſheafe cleere of charges, had better give the fifth acre of all their lands for gleab-land unto the Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Thus then their tythes of 2000 l. amount in valuation unto the fifth part of 2000 l. which is 400 l. &amp; this 400 l. for the Miniſter being taken out of 2000 l. which is the whole revenue of the Pariſh land, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines 1600 l. to be divided amongſt 499. men and women, who are the Pariſhioners, which is not full 3 l. 4 s. 1 d. ½. a pecce, whereas the miniſter devours 400 l. which is more than any 124. of his Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners enjoy, upon ſuch a calculation, ſuppoſing them to be all poore, or all rich alike. And yet the unſatiableneſſe of theſe Clergy-bellies is not here with content, but they lay claime to tithes on houſe rent, and <hi>the tenth part of whatſoever any perſon of any profeſſion, doth any wayes lawfully
<pb facs="tcp:113400:2"/>advance, to be due unto the Miniſter of the Goſpel both by the law of God and man, unleſſe ſome ſpeciall cuſtome, compoſition or priviledge of the place allowed by</hi> law, exempt him: They are the very words of that Epiſcopall, Presbyteriall, Ambodexterous Tythe-Champion (for Tythes are a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon motto to both parties.) Dr. <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> an eminent member of this preſent Aſſembly, in a Diſcourſe of his entituled, <hi>A new diſcovery of perſonall Tythes, or the tenth part of mens cleare gaines, &amp;c.</hi> p. 1. as I finde it obſerved in <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, Chap. 2 about <hi>Chriſts order and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples practice corcerning the Miniſters maintenance, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why tro did not the Dr. with his brethren in covetouſneſſe, as well claime tythes of children, as of fruit and perſonall gaines, whereof we finde not the leaſt mention in either of the Teſtaments? Surely they would not continue ſo indulgent, they would not bate us our children, could they but get it once enacted, that it might bee lawfull for them to ſell tythe children in the market as well as tythe pigs: and to deale clearly, the Leviticall law, from whence they ſeeke to colour tythes, ſubjected every firſt borne, whether it were of man or beaſt, unto this tax of tithes, it fell unto the Prieſts ſhare, Lev. 13.2. c. 22.29. Numb. 18.15. the Leviticall Prieſt was to have the firſt borne of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, unleſſe they were redeemed, and our Engliſh Prieſts, could they but get an Ordinance of Lords and Commons for it, as well as tythes, I ſhould not truſt their curteſies.</p>
            <p>Tell me, good Reader, who ever thou art, didſt thou ever think theſe fair pretending Clergymen, every one whereof having devoured above 124. of his brethren by divine right, as they alleadge, their tythe patent which they ſay God granted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould be yet, thus Canine-like hungry; this craving as of their own meer phantaſie &amp; invention to lay title un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tenth part of all clear gains beſides, which would be many times more then the Leviticall tithes amounted to (the gaine of handicraft myſteries and trading, being by manifold, more conſiderable than the encreaſe of all the land in England?) and that which is yet more irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall and peſtiferous, they will have it whether we will or no, they wreſt it from us by violence, they rob us of it: 'Tis not my deſire thou ſhouldeſt take this calculation upon truſt: Nature hath taught every reaſonable man Arithmeticke enough to make triall of it, the truth thereof, when thou thy ſelf perceiveſt and conſidereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the conſequence, I ſhall not ſo much deſire thee to ſtand amazed, as to contribute thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient for curing our Clergymen of this their deſperate <hi>covetouſnes,</hi> which is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> Col. 3.5, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113400:3"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men, Brethren, and Fathers:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Could not chooſe but give you notice of a Deſigne diſcovered unto mee, of no ſmall a party which at preſent is conſpiring, how the poſſeſſions of Biſhops, Deanes and Chapters, &amp;c. which by our Anceſtors were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for publique and pious uſes, may become their peculiar inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and totally diſcourage poſterity from all charitable legacies, when they ſhall ſee them alienated to ſuch qui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te contrary purpoſes.</p>
            <p>I underſtand likewiſe of ſeverall Petitions by multitudes of the moſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious free-borne ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> demonſtrating how unjuſt it is, that a ſmall number, who in complement call themſelves our <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſhould at their owne pleaſure become our <hi>Maſters</hi> and ſo contrary to the ſubjects liberty, force from us the fifth part of the whole Kingdome in valuation without either articles or conſent, and that which is worſt of all, even not to be longer endured by ſuch as make conſcience of any thing, they lay claime to it by <hi>Divine right,</hi> and for ſuch ſervices, as to many ſeem little leſſe than Antichriſtian, or Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous: 'Tis frivolous for you to diſtinguiſh between a conſcience truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and contrarily; for, unleſſe you will pretend your arguments to be like the peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, <hi>Phil. 4.7.</hi> you muſt unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably permit men, even every particular man for himſelfe, to reſolve the whole Scripture and every part thereof into a full perſwaſion of his owne heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whatſoever he is to practiſe or believe, <hi>Rom. 14.5.22.23.</hi> either grant this, or burne your Bibles, how many ſoever differing tranſlations, with their whole impreſſions, as have been brought unto you, ſince you doe but teach your Lay-people to ſuſpect them all, whilſt you your ſelves will not be ruled by any, in any mans judgement beſides your owne.</p>
            <p>A word to the wiſe ſhould be enough; It is of ſo great intereſt and conſequence to this whole Kingdome, for one reſpect or other, to demoliſh and root out the very memory of this Tith-Idoll, which all other Reformed Chriſtians have long ſince abominated, that it concernes you to looke out ſome other maintenance leſſe ſcandalous, and more Goſpel-like.</p>
            <p>But you'l ſay perhaps, you have maintenance allotted you by Ordinance of Parliament: what an Ordinance of Parliament? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reverence Ordinances of Parliament; but, me thinks, you ſhould rather flye for refuge to Chriſts Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance;
<pb facs="tcp:113400:3"/>Ordinances of Parliament are repealable, what one Parliament beſtowes upon you, another Parliament may take away, but Chriſts Ordinances, are like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, unchangeable; what ever you thinke of him, doubtleſſe you cannot leave him for a better Maſter: Try then a little, compare the Ordinances together, looke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you leap, if ye be Men, if Chriſtians, conſider which may prove the ſureſt, the better title.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ordained that <hi>they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>9.14.</hi> that is, they ſhould have ſuch a livelihood as is ſet out, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the Goſpel, which is the free benevolence and bounty of their brethren, and if you will have it in Chriſts owne words unto the true Diſciples, <hi>That into what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever houſe they enter they ſhould remain eating and drinking ſuch things as were ſet before them, Luk. 10.5.7.8.</hi> and <hi>having food and rayment they ſhould be there with content, 1 Tim. 6.8, On the other ſide:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, <hi>Die Veneris, 8</hi> Novemb. <hi>1644.</hi> Ordaine <hi>that every perſon or perſons within the Realme of</hi> England <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>ſhall pay all and ſingular tithes, offerings, oblations, obventions, rates for tithes, and all other duties commonly known by the name of tithes, unto the reſpective owners both Lay and Eccleſiaſticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the effect of Chriſts Ordinance, with that of the Lords and Commons in Parliament: I ſhall not ſeek to make enmity betwixt them, and I hope every Reader, will, in time, ſee how far forth they will run parallel. What will you more then? Our Saviour, you ſee, has by an Ordinance of heaven provided for you both food and rayment, requiring you by his Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to be therewith content.</p>
            <p>But me thinks I heare you murmuring that this Goſpel maintenance, being by the Spirit of God termed a <hi>free gift, 2 Cor. 8.4. Phil. 4.17. a matter of bounty, and not grudging, 2 Cor. 9.5.</hi> you have not the conſcience, what ever your practice be, to think you may command it at your pleaſure, have it whether your Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners will or no; and 'tis irkſome to your high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>indedneſſe, to ſuppoſe your ſelves their Almeſmen, and live on their benevolence. But what advantage have you by your <hi>tithe Ordinance?</hi> how, I pray, will you get your tithes, if the people will not pay them? how can you force them to it, if the people be reſolved on the contrary? Oh! I know your meaning, you'l diſtraine their goods, impriſon their perſons, and with ſome vexatious accurſed act or other, you'l take away their lives, and all they have together: but are you ſo ſtout and ſturdy (not being perhaps above one for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of your Lay-brethren) as to imagine that a Regiment of Blackcoats, can, with a bare humane Ordinance of tithes, defeat a whole Nation, both of their Chriſtian and Civill priviledges? beleeve me <hi>bold Souldiers,</hi> you will finde hard ſervice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it; the peoples eyes begin to be open, and if you diſcover the nakedneſſe of your unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable covetouſneſſe a little more, they will, queſtionleſſe, ſo far reflect on the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe clear words in our Saviours Commiſſion unto his true Diſciples, ſaying,
<pb facs="tcp:113400:4"/>
               <hi>Freely you have received, freely give,</hi> Mat. <hi>10.8.</hi> that your mercenary praying and preaching will grow contemptible, and our exerciſing Weavers, Feltmakers, Coblers, &amp;c. be found more to reſemble true Miniſters of the Goſpel, than your lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctorſhips. But becauſe I ſee ſome of you are not aſhamed to be thought Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, who take for granted that you may, &amp; ought to be provident, no leſſe than your Lay-brethren, both for your ſelves and families; I hope <hi>I</hi> ſhall not prove an unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Monitor, if <hi>I</hi> be inſtant with you to ponder ſeriouſly, whether it be for your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to wave Chriſts Ordinance, and adhere unto the Parliaments for maintenance.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Lords and Commons have been bountifull unto you, moſt tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently bountifull, no Proteſtant State did ever doe the like! (<hi>I</hi> wiſh it were well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) they give you tithes with an &amp;c. offerings, oblations, &amp;c above a tenth part, even above the fifth, in a juſt valuation, of all that the land produceth: But what if they ſhould give you halfe, or three quarters of all we have? can you enjoy it longer then good people pleaſe to pay it you? <hi>I</hi> hope, it will not be impertinent, towards meaning you from a Canonicall obedience, by minding you that there have been many laws agreed on in Parliament, which never had execution afterwards, for want of a ſecondary, and more effectuall aſſenting of the people in generall, whom the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment does but repreſent. You know, likewiſe, much may be ſaid, both from Laws and Cuſtome, in behalfe of the Kings Prerogative, Revenues, and not much leſſe than a boundleſſe ſubjection, and yet you ſee, how little he hath of either for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; a Prince can reigne no longer over the perſons of his ſubjects, than hee can maſter their affections; A uſurped tyrannicall power is of ſhort continuance, but the free conſent and love of a people, is that only, which makes all Empire durable and happy.</p>
            <p>Doe not then ſeeth your ſelvees up, that a Nation which has been at charge of ſo many millions (as ſome Accountants thinke the Visited Provinces never had, to ſpend upon all their
<gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> years war) with the loſſe of ſo many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thouſand ſlaine, in red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eming their propriety and priviledges from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of evill counſellours, will afterwards proſtrate themſelves, both ſoule and body, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your diſcretion? doe you thinke a people, which capitulates with their Maſter, will ſubmit unto their Miniſters? is it not a pretty mock ſhow, a contradiction, a very lie, for Miniſters to be carvers of their owne wages, whether their Maſters will or no? to pay themſelves out of their Maſters purſes, under pretence of adminiſtring to them ſpirituall things, and yet reſtraine them from participating thereof, when they ſee good, or but pretend to ſee it? it may not, it cannot, it muſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t long endure.</p>
            <p>Ponder then a litle, which may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beſt win upon the peoples diſpoſition, whether your ſubmitting unto their Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an charity which to many of the Independent may proves more beneficiall then tithes, or to continue contraſting with them, as his Majeſtie with his evill Councellours have done, to the haza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding fall</p>
            <p>Forbeare then to take too much upon you; Encroach neither upon your Brethrens Spiritualities, nor Temporalties; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſuch power and principles, as may juſtly move the Civill State to be jealous of you, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> like enough (for they have both be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red and been liberall to you beyond deſert) they will diſtribute or appropriate unto your T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, all the poſſeſſions, that unrighteous mammon, of Biſhops, Deans and Chapters, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Believe me <hi>Friends,</hi> they are worth the looking after, and if, through your owne careleſſenes, or your enemies vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance you miſſe thereof, you may like enough be put to get a living by labouring in ſome honeſt calling, as your neighbours do: Be w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe as Serpents, and (Gramercy Biſhop) you may yet fare well.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. line 10. read of ſuch. ibid. l. 34. neither can. p 4 l.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. due for. p. 7. l. 5. much is. p. 15. l. 8. he demure, p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> l. 11. may be p. 18. l. 35 ſame coat.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113400:4"/>
            <head>Certaine briefe Obſervations concerning the inſtitution and paying of tythes in the Old Teſtament, with the Miniſters maintenance in the New; neither of which was levied in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive manner, nor could poſſibly become a ſweet ſavour in the noſtrills of the Lord, had they not beene given freely, as a matter of bounty, not grudgingly.</head>
            <p>HAving often in my ſaddeſt thoughts bewayled the lamentable condition, which Gods deareſt people are brought into, through that accurſed yoake of a forced uniformity, which is endeavoured to be put upon their conſciences, and caſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what evill ſpirit it was, that had ſo vaſt a malignant influence throughout the world; at laſt, it appeared cleerly unto my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it could not poſſibly, for the moſt part, bee any other, beſides that Grand <hi>Idol</hi> or rather divell of <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> which is <hi>the root of all evill</hi> and miſchiefe that happeneth unto mankind, Col. 3.5. 1 Tim. 6.10. Act. 19.19.20. c. 16.16, 17, 18, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Then; pondering with my ſelfe, how this Imp of covetouſneſſe, as it produced perſecution, was ſuckled and maintain'd; I found at laſt, that it muſt neceſſarily be both begotten and continued by that ſpecious golden wedge of <hi>Goſpel-tythes,</hi> which an illegitimate Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> had at firſt, only <hi>Achan-like,</hi> purloyned from their brethren, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards preſumptuouſly intituled upon God himſelfe, that both they and their ſucceſſors, might with an uncontroleable ſecurity live and dye ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feting upon the fatneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>But if any man perceive not how it comes about, that a <hi>coveting after tythes begets perſecution;</hi> I anſwer, that theſe <hi>Tythmongers,</hi> as <hi>Eſaiah</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes thoſe of his time, 56.11. terming them <hi>greedy dogs, which can never be ſatisfied, are ſo intent upon the gaine which commeth from their quarters,</hi> (that ſince they cannot for ſhame require contributions from ſuch as refuſe out of conſcience to joyne with them in Church duties) they put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon inveying with all manner of exaſperation and bitterneſſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuch as differ from them, whether in diſcipline or doctrine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually inſencing both their Pariſhoners and Civill Magiſtrates againſt them as Heretickes, ſuch as hold dangerous opinions deſtructive to the State, not to be endured upon any quarter and compoſition, becauſe no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113400:5"/>accommodation can bee to their purpoſe wherein <hi>Tythes</hi> are not the princ pall article to be agreed upon.</p>
            <p>In contemplation hereof, I put my ſelfe againe to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (though I know there is ſcarce any one how vile ſoever, whether for practice or opinion only, who <hi>pretends</hi> not to be Goſpel-proofe, but I ſpeake to ſuch of whom <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt ſaid, <hi>Search the Scriptures for in them yee thinke to have eternall life,</hi> Joh. 5.39. to ſuch I ſay, who would be thought to have the Scripture for their rule, and really expect ſalvation by living according to that rule) and am willing to give a faithfull, though briefe relation thereof, on ſuch particulars I mean, as have not to my knowledge beene publiſhed by others, to ſhew how vaine the ground is of pretending <hi>Goſpel-tythes,</hi> and how dangerous to continue them.</p>
            <p>The firſt place I meet with ſpeaking of <hi>Tythes</hi> is Gen. 14.20. where <hi>Abraham is ſaid to give Melchiſedeck tythes of all,</hi> that is, of all the ſpoile only, which he had in the victory againſt the foure Kings in reſcuing of his brother <hi>Lot,</hi> whom they had taken priſoner, as you may ſee in the ſame Chapter: and though it be objected that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes to tell the <hi>Hebrews</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> gave iythings of <hi>all things</hi> unto <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeck,</hi> Heb. 7.2. yet you may find that the ſame Apoſtle in v. 4 whilſt be would magnifie the preheminence of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> in his relation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving tythes, before <hi>Abraham</hi> paying tythes, inſtances only in his pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him tythes of the ſpoyls, but had <hi>Abraham</hi> paid tythes of all things he poſſeſſed, the Apoſtles argument might have thereby been ſo much more improved, if he had urg'd it. But this paying tythes unto <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was ſupereminently typicall, as <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was a type of Chriſt, Heb. 8.4.5. and in that reſpect only, <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes that <hi>Melchiſedeck received tythes of Abraham bleſſing him that had the promiſe, and without contradiction the leſſe is bleſſed of the greater,</hi> Heb. 7.6.7. for even the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> is ſaid to pay tythes unto <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> in the loynes of <hi>Abraham</hi> Heb. 7.9.10. and the <hi>Levites</hi> could not be properly ſaid in the ſame time and reſpect, both to pay tythes in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and yet receive tythes in <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> ſo that this is no Scripture for their purpoſe; the very tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> paid tythes unto <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> and therefore neither they, nor a ſuppoſitions off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of theirs much leſſe, pretend with any other than a brazen-face and countenance, to derive a juſt grant and title from <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving tythes; but beſides theſe words of <hi>Pauls</hi> to the Heb. 7.5. The <hi>Levites</hi> who received the office of Prieſt-hood, had commandement for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113400:5"/>receiving tythes <hi>according to the Law,</hi> dee plainly teach us that the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tythes, the tenths of all encreaſe, as our ſelfe-ſeeking Clergy will have it underſtood, began not till the law was given, and that the <hi>Levites</hi> had the Prieſthood entailed upon their Tribe, and conſequently that till then there was no commandement for paying them, nor any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy warranted to receive them.</p>
            <p>Gen. 28.20, 21, 22. We finde that <hi>Jacob</hi> when hee went to <hi>Laban</hi> at <hi>Padan-Aram</hi> to take a wife, being on the way of <hi>Luz</hi> ſo called anciently, but by him named <hi>Bethel,</hi> v. 19. in the morning after his viſion, he made a vow unto God, ſaying, <hi>If God will be with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e and keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> use in this way that I goe, and will give me bread to eat, and raiment to put o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo that I come again to my fathers houſe in peace, then, of all that thou ſhalt give me, I will ſurely give the tenth unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this occaſion, it will not be amiſſe, 1. to remember that all vows ought to be voluntary; ſuch is this promiſing of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Abrahams</hi> pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tythes unto <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> neither of them being commanded, nor ſo much as uſually practiſed from <hi>Abraham</hi> his firſt paying to this time of <hi>Jacob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> vowing them: for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> had been obliged, or but accu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>omed to pay tythes from the time that <hi>Abraham</hi> firſt paid them unto <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck,</hi> this preſent vowing of his would have been different from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a vow, which is of ſome new thing not cuſtomarily, much leſſe obligatorily performed before; nay, it might have ſeemed a kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding God Almighty, in pretending to doe ſome extraordinary ſervice, prefixing thereunto the ſacred preamble and title of a vow, but in the upſhot, not ſo much as promiſe more, than was both due and ordinarily diſcha ged before: then ſecondly, theſe tythes <hi>Jacob</hi> vowes not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to pay them, till he returne unto his fathers houſe in peace, which we know was many years after, and is a certaine argument that till then he made no reckoning of paying a continuall fixed tythe or tenth part of what God gave him at leaſt we ſee no example of it.</p>
            <p>Levit. 27.30 32 'tis ſaid, <hi>all the tythe of the land both of the ſeed of the ground, and of the fruit of the trees is the Lords, it is holy to the Lord, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tythe of bullock and of ſheep, and of all that gooth under the red, the tenth of all ſhall be holy unto the Lord:</hi> and v. 34. 'tis ſaid, <hi>theſe are the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord by</hi> Moſes <hi>unto the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in Mount Sinai;</hi> ſo that before that time, there was no commmandment for paying of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Theſe tithes being thus ſet apart by the Lord, are in Numb. 18 21.24. appropriated unto the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> but neither to be enjoyed by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113400:6"/>
               <hi>Le vites,</hi> nor paid by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> untill they came into the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> as appeares in that the Lord ſaies, <hi>I have given it them, therefore ſhall they poſſeſſe no inheritance among the children of</hi> Iſrael, v. 24. that is, in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> as is likwiſe impoſed upon <hi>Aaron,</hi> v. 20. for before that time, both <hi>Aarons</hi> and the other families of the <hi>Levites</hi> had their proper inheritances and poſſeſſions, as had the other Tribes, Deut. 18.8.</p>
            <p>Here then we may obſerve, that by Gods ordinance there was no tythes of any thing due, ſave of the ſeed of the ground, of the fruit of the trees, and of foure footed beaſts, Lev. 27.30.32. both fiſh and fowle were free, much leſſe doe we finde here any tythes, any exciſe put upon mens labours; that was likely thought a duty to be exacted and collected rather by Publicans, then by a conſecrated Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> concerning whom the Lord ſaid, that, from what time their tythes grew due, <hi>it ſhould be a law for ever throughout their generations, that among the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>they poſſeſſe no inheritance,</hi> Num. 18.23. which I much wonder how ſuch as claime tythes at this day doe yet diſpence withall; I meane, how theſe pretended Clergy-men ſhould both receive tythes, and yet enjoy all manner of inheritances and poſſeſſions in common with the Laity.</p>
            <p>Then; as we finde in Numb. 18.29. the <hi>Levites</hi> were cut of their tythes to pay the one tenth for an offering unto <hi>Aaron</hi> and his family, who was alſo of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> Gen. 4.14. and for this reſpect, as alſo in that the Lord gave him the offerings of all hallowed things, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meat-offerings, ſin-offerings or treſpaſſe-offerings, v. 8 9. he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to have no inheritance in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Lord promiſing him to be his part among the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> v. 20. Now, unleſſe this pretended Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> can finde out one beſides the Pope, who like <hi>Aaron,</hi> has as good a title to the heave-offering, as they themſelves have unto the tythes of all; me thinks they ſhould be jealous of their owne title, and let it fall to ground for ſhame, if not for modeſty.</p>
            <p>Beſides the tithes of all encreaſe, the <hi>Iewes</hi> were with their houſhold to eat another tenth thereof at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in the ſight of God, Deut. 14.23. but if the way were far, ſo that they could not carry the tithes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conveniently, then they might ſell it at their homes, and carrying the mony unto <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> buy what their hearts deſired, and there, eat it before the Lord, rejoycing with their houſholds, v. 24, 25, 26. This tithe ſome conceive to be due of feaſting two years in three, though the text may well be underſtood of every year, v. 23. for all that I can find to the contrary.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113400:6"/>
            <p>But I wonder whether they were thus to ſpend a whole tithe in feaſting, as the text ſeems to inſinuate, v. 23.26. and the <hi>Jewes</hi> even to this day ſpend both much money and time in feaſting, or whether they ſaw a part thereof thus ſpent at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> leaving the reſt for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the <hi>Levites,</hi> as they did the other tithes.</p>
            <p>Then we finde <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.28, 29. &amp;c. 26.12. that every third yeare they were to lay up one tenth in ſtore at their owne habitations, for the uſe of the <hi>Levites,</hi> ſtrangers, fatherleſſe and widows; ſo that by this calculation, they paid and ſpent two tenths yearly, if not full three tenths every third year, of all their cattell, and what the earth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> tells us, P. 110.4. That our Saviour was <hi>a Prieſt after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedech;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies that <hi>he pertained unto another Tribe, whereof no man ſerved at the altar;</hi> and that <hi>it was evident that our Lord ſprang out of</hi> Judah, <hi>concerning which tribe</hi> Moſes <hi>ſpake nothing touching the Prieſthood,</hi> Heb. 7.13, 14. &amp; v. 12. <hi>if the Prieſthood be changed, thou of neceſſity muſt there be a change of the Law:</hi> from whence, together with v. 5. which ſaies that <hi>the ſonnes of</hi> Levi, <hi>who received the office of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood had a commandement to take tythes according to the Law;</hi> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Leviticall</hi> tithes, the tenths of all things are as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolliſhed as the <hi>Leviticall</hi> Prieſthood it ſelfe, v. 12. ſo that the preſent Miniſters under the Goſpel can no more pretend unto the one, than to the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What ever tythes were due unto <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> the ſame became due afterwards, and were payable unto our Saviour, who was a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> (as the whole <hi>Laviticall</hi> Prieſthood was typicall, a ſhadow of heavenly things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.4, 5.) and of whom <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech</hi> was a type; that is, they were to be fulfilled in our Saviour, to whom only all homage and ſubjection is due from <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his poſterity, and from whom only both <hi>Abraham</hi> and his poſterity are to expect their bleſſing: ſo that as our Saviour, laid no claime, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Judaicall</hi> or <hi>Leviticall</hi> tythes which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies muſt neceſſarily be changed with the Prieſthood; much leſſe ought they who will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves true Miniſters and followers of Chriſt, to bee ſo greedy after them, ſince it renders them ſo much unlike their Maſter.</p>
            <p>Being evident then that reall or materiall tythes have never beene due, ſince our Saviour that other Prieſt as <hi>Paul</hi> calls him, aroſe after
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113400:7"/>ſimilitude of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> who was not made a Prieſt after the law of carnall commandement, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.15.16. it followeth that all ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have, or doe exact and compell men to pay them tythes, doe but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ob them in effect, and thereby become accountable both to God and man.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> in a Treatiſe entituled <hi>The Revenue of the Goſpell is tythes due to the Ministery by the word of God.</hi> c. 7. p 52. &amp;c. ſaies to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that <hi>our Saviour received tythes in the New Teſtament,</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prove it from theſe words to the Heb. 7.8. <hi>Here men dye that receive tythes, but there be receiveth them of whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> witneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth;</hi> and will have whatſoever is ſpoken of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> to be meant of Chriſt from v. 13.14. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>He of whom t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe things are ſpoken pertaineth to another tribe, whereof no men ſerved at the altar, for it is evident that our Lord ſprang out of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how unwarrantably, or little to the purpoſe, will eaſily appear, if we conſider not only <hi>who</hi> this is that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>receiveth tythes and liveth,</hi> diſtinguiſhing him from thoſe <hi>who received tythes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed;</hi> but alſo what this <hi>there</hi> ſignified, which is likewiſe differenced from <hi>here;</hi> and if the men which received tithes and dyed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth tithes and liveth for ever, be not one and the ſame (which may well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reconciled, whilſt the one was typicall, and the other the antitype) then muſt there needs bee two receiving of tithes, which how far forth ſo ever they be conſidered on, or ſpun out in frivolous diſcourſes; what will it make to the pretence of a whole tenth of every thing to bee <hi>now</hi> due unto the Clergy?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe Chriſt did, or doth ſtill, in ſome ſenſe receive tithes: 'tis in no other ſenſe, be it what it will, than in the very ſame ſenſe, wherein be received them under the Law even when he was on earth; or now as hee is aſcended into heaven both as our High Prieſt and ſacrifice, v. 27. which would evidently condemne all ſuch of moſt accurſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riledge and blaſphemy, who ſhould lay claime to them by ſuch a title.</p>
            <p>Doe wee finde it any where commanded to give materiall, real tithes of all we have unto our Saviour? did he take or ſo much as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them when he was on earth as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>MMelchiſedeck</hi> did? i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not the Prieſthood which the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of changed, v. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and there withall the very law even that of tithes changed, as well as other particulars thereof, as that which made nothing perfect, v. 19.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113400:7"/>
            <p>But the truth is, that if tithes have any eſtabliſhment by <hi>Abrahams</hi> giving <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> the tenth of all his ſpoyles, it would follow, that the Clergy ſhould primarily have the tenth of all prize-goods and ſpoyles of War, particularly of theſe preſent Wars of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſo much plainly affirmed by Mr. <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lke Roberts</hi> in his <hi>Revenue of the Goſpel,</hi> c. 6. p. 30, 31. which I hope not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Souldiery, but the State alſo will ſeriouſly conſider of, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a good conſcience, by making reſtitution to them, or requiring an account of their judgement in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>And now as touching what is ſaid in the New Teſtament concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Miniſters maintenance, I finde not there the leaſt footſteps that tythes or any firſt allowance inſtead thereof was either made pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of, or commanded; it was left to be a free-will offering, as moſt ſutable to the Goſpel; only the equity there of is hinted at in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall paſſages; as, <hi>The workman is worthy of his meat,</hi> Matth. 10.10. <hi>The labourer is worthy of his hire,</hi> Luke 10.7. <hi>Who gooth to Warfare any time at his owne charge? Who planteth a vineyard and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who ſeedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock? even ſo hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the Goſpell ſhould live by the Goſpell,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7.14. <hi>They which miniſter about holy things, live on the things of the Temple, and they which wait on the altar are partakers with the altar,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.13. This is all that the New Teſtament teaches us, and that by way of equity only, how to proportion out a maintenance to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Then, as touching both the Miniſters and Beleevers practice in this particular. 1. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that <hi>he had kept himſelf from being burthen ſome unto them, and ſo was reſolved to keep himſelfe as the truth of Chriſt was in him, and that no man ſhould hind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that beaſting of his</hi> in the Regions of Achaia, 2 Cor. 11.9.10. But in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> c. 9. v. 15.18.23. he inſinuates, that it were better for him to dye, than that this boaſting of his, of not making the Goſpell charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſhould be prevented; neither was this <hi>Paul</hi> practice for himſelfe only, but it ſeems he gave <hi>Titus</hi> and ſuch others as he ſent unto them, expreſſe order that their Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry likewiſe ſhould not become bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 Cor. 12, 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>And when he came to Epheſus, he called the Elders of the Church together, Act. 20.17. and having had a large diſcoure with them wherein he told them that he had not ſhuned to declare unto them all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113400:8"/>the counſell of God, v. 27. hee put them notwithſtanding in minde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine how he had coveted no mans ſilver, nor gold, nor apparrell; yea that they themſelves knew, how thoſe hands of his had miniſtred unto his neceſſities, and to them that were with them, v. 33.34. adding that he had ſhewed them all things, how that <hi>ſo labouring</hi> they ought to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the weake, v. 35.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Paul</hi> with <hi>Silvanus</hi> and <hi>Timotheus,</hi> told the Theſſalonians, that they wrought with labour night and day that they might not bee chargeable to any of them, and that they might be an example unto them to doe the like, even unto them of the Miniſtery, if there be any who could ſay with <hi>Paul</hi> that they had power to eat and drinke, that they had power to forbeare working as well as any of the Apoſtles, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4, 5, 6. Even ſuch I ſay, are required by <hi>Paul, Silvanus</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> to worke with labour and travell night and day that they may not be chargeable unto any, 2 Theſ. 3.8 9.</p>
            <p>However we may not thinke ſo uncharitably of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that they did not, and that liberally too, contribute unto their Miniſters, I meane, ſuch as were able: <hi>Paul</hi> beares witneſſe of their readineſſe both to the <hi>Romans, Corinthians</hi> and <hi>Philippians,</hi> certifying us that they were willing even beyond their power, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3.4. and that in ſo large a meaſure, as the text ſaies in ſeverall places that <hi>they ſold their poſſeſſions, and parted them to all men as they had need, laid them at the Apoſtles feet, or had all things in common, ſo that no man ſaid, that ought of the things hee poſſeſſed was his owne,</hi> Acts 2.44.45. Chap. 4.32.35.</p>
            <p>But as the Scripture ſayes, not many noble, not many rich were called, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. ſo it is cleare in all hiſtory, that the poverty of the Primitive Chriſtians was generall; and ſo it may have been obſerved to be in all ages even till theſe preſent dayes; from whence wee finde it ſo often objected to the diſparagement of ſuch as now ſeeke after truth, what are they but a company of poore, baſe, contemptible peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aye nothing to loſe? as if there were nothing worth lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing beſides the rich mens Idols, of ſuperfluity and pelfe, who in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to their owne ſaying, muſt thinke nothing beſides theſe worth getting: But alas I have not ſuch poore contemptible Chriſtians, in theſe men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> account, ſoules to loſe, as well as they? Ile promiſe them, they have ſoules to ſave, better then they: The truth is, they want the temptation of wealth and greatneſſe, which too too commonly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwayes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113400:8"/>men from ſeeking after truth, as it pleaſes God to diſcover it by peace-meales, and in ſuch manner only, as we grow capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; being apt to thinke they were the <hi>poore</hi> Chriſtians of whom it was ſaid, that <hi>from John Baptiſt untill the Apoſtles time the Kingdome of heaven ſuffered violence, and the violent took it by force,</hi> Mat. 11.12. I hope the Reader will pardon this digreſſion, and ſo I returne to the point againe.</p>
            <p>It is acknowledged then that under the Goſpell, a competent and comfortable maintenance is due unto the Miniſtery; yet this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did, not only, not capitulate for, but <hi>Paul</hi> alleadges two moſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall reaſons, which might prevaile with any man that were not a very muckworme, or had any ſparks of piety remaining in him, that they ſhould betake themſelves to any lawfull calling, and worke even night and day with their owne hands, as hee did, rather then be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to need the benevolence of their brethren, ſaying, <hi>It is more bleſſed to give than to receive,</hi> Act. 20.35. and that <hi>the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for their children,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.14.</p>
            <p>And if at any time the Apoſtles did ſtand in need, and that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, of their owne Chriſtian diſpoſition, gave them any thing, the Apoſtles ſtill received it as a gift, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3.4. <hi>a matter of bounty,</hi> c. 9.5. expreſly declaring that <hi>they ſought not theirs but them,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.13, 14. Nay, <hi>Paul</hi> would not have accepted of a gift, even to the reliefe of his neceſſities, had it not beene rather to give them an occaſion to ſhew forth the fruits of their proficiency of their charity, that it might ſo much the more abundantly redound to their account, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.15, 16, 17. Had <hi>Paul</hi> been the moſt eminent Rhetoritian, of his time, as hee was no meane one; had he ſtudied to deliver this notion of his in ſtraines of higheſt expreſſions; I cannot conceive how it was poſſible to out goe himſelfe herein; but we muſt impute it to the ſufficiency of that Spirit which gave him matter of glorying above all other Apoſtles, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21.23.</p>
            <p>Thus we finde in ſundry Scriptures declared, and particularly in <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.9. and 18.1. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 13.4. <hi>En.</hi> 44.28. that in the diſtribution of the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> was to have no inheritance, the Lord promiſing that he would be their inheritance; but in regard that he had aſſigned unto them all his owns <hi>lot and ſhare,</hi> which was the <hi>tythes of all that the earth pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Lev. 27.30.32, beſides that of <hi>foure foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed beaſts,</hi> as alſo <hi>all things hallowed,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113400:9"/>
               <hi>meat offerings, ſin offerings or treſpaſſe offerings,</hi> v. 8.9. which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a larger ſtock and proportion than if they had had aſſigned them ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> part of the whole land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> it may be demanded, to what put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then does God ſay he will be the <hi>Levites</hi> portion? I anſwer, that it may likely bee the Lords intention, that the <hi>Levites</hi> whom hee had drawne unto himſelfe by a neerer relation of office and ſervice, ſhould not have any certaine permanent inheritance in <hi>Canaan,</hi> as the other Tribes, but that they ſhould relie upon the tythes, and ſuch other duties as God had firſt aſſumed unto himſelfe, and then allotted unto them, which being more uncertaine, becauſe of the Iſraelites would not pay them theſe duties, theſe tithes, I finde no coercive power appointed to compell them thereunto, the Lord would notwithſtanding have them relye thereon, or rather on himſelfe, who promiſed to be their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, their portion, that is to provide for the <hi>Levites,</hi> though their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſhould faile of paying tythes; for in other reſpects the Lord was the inheritance of all the Iſraelites, all alike; hee failes not to take care and charge of all that truſt in him: juſt ſo is it with Chriſts Miniſters in the New Teſtament; a maintenance is due unto them from their brethren, but in ſuch a manner, that whoſoever will not give them any, cannot be compelled unto it; and from ſuch as give it them, they are to acknowledge it as a <hi>gift,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8 4. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>But leaſt it ſhould bee thought a bare aſſertion of mine, that then was no compulſive power allotted by God for conſtraining the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites to pay their tithes; let the Reader be pleaſed to obſerve how it is ſaid in <hi>Samuel,</hi> that the ſonnes of <hi>Eli</hi> came with a fleſh hooke, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it into the pot when the people offered ſacrifice, tooke all the meat that came up for the Prieſt, and this they did <hi>per force</hi> ſometimes when they ſo pleaſed, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.13. to 16. but we finde they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>ſennes of Belial for it,</hi> v. 12. and the text ſayes, <hi>their ſin was very greet before the Lord,</hi> and that for this cauſe <hi>men abhorred the offering of the Lord</hi> v. 17. Beſides we ſee in <hi>Malachi</hi> 3.9.10. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.10.11.12. when the people refuſed to pay tythes, the Lord complained of them excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly by his Prophets, but never gave the Magiſtrate order to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them for it, or ſo much as reprehended him for omitting it.</p>
            <p>But let us debate the caſe a little further with theſe greedy muck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme Tith-mongers; doe we not ſee by experience how few of them would bee contented that their Congregations, their Pariſhes ſhould violently d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ine them, not ſuffering them to depart, when they found
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113400:9"/>opportunity to remove themſelves unto a larger maintenance? and yet if their Pariſhioners ſhould ſay, Sir, you expect, require; nay, even compell us, hitherto, to pay you tithes, the tenth part of all we have; but now there is a godly man, who would be glad of the opportunity to adminiſter unto us ſuch ſpirituall things as our ſoules delight in, and ſtand to our free will offerings for his malntenance, who would bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſatisfied with one halfe, even any portion what ever it bee, that commeth from us voluntarily.</p>
            <p>Wee entreat you therefore give us leave to make uſe of this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in favour both of our purſes and our ſoules: doe you finde theſe ſelfe-ſeeking Clergimen would bee contented to lay downe their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Commiſſion? No, 'tis too too evident they would not: Their pretences are; Our livings are given us for our lives, we have as good a title to them as you have to your lands; Nay, they ſticke not to flie higher, and even Biſhop-like to argue their tenour, <hi>providentia Dei,</hi> by divine right.</p>
            <p>But is this equall brethren? Does Chriſtianity engage us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our Civill rights, our very reaſon? may theſe Clergymen who in complement ſometimes pleaſe to call themſelves our Miniſters, our ſervants, (though like their Great Grandfather the Pope who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes <hi>ſervus ſervorum Dei,</hi> even whilſt bee expects that Kings and Emperours ſhould wait upon him) and have their livelihoods out of our purſes, thus eaſily become our Maſters, intrude themſelves at firſt upon us whether we will or no, continue with us as long as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves liſt, take upon them to keep us from the Ordinances when they will, preach what traſh and trumpery they pleaſe, exact the tithes, which in effect is one fiſt part of our whole eſtate, as is made appeare upon calculation in the Epiſtle to the Reader; and yet leave us at their owne pleaſure, when it makes for their advantage? <hi>Micha</hi> his Prieſt when he could get no more g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſome imployment, agreed with him by the yeare for 10 <hi>ſhekels of ſilver, a ſuit of apparrell, and his dyet, Judges,</hi> 17.10.11. but ſo ſo one as hee met with opportunity of becomming Prieſt unto a whole Tribe, he laid hold thereon with joy, c. 18. v. 19.20. even thus theſe Merchants of the Goſpel; none in appearance at firſt more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and officious then they, untill they get into a Benefice or Locture endeavouring themſelves what poſſibly they can, that, beſides their tithes, they may raiſe the price of their benevolences; but if a more fat Parſonage preſent it ſelfe, <hi>Quis niſi mentis inops ablatum reſpuit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113400:10"/>is their practicall divinity, they account it the greateſt folly under heaven to refuſe it.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe like enough the Anſwerer of Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> 12. Queſtions uſed theſe words concerning them, pag. 20. <hi>May it not well be ſaid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Micah</hi> 3.11. <hi>that the Clergy teach for hire, and Propheſie for mony, which God by him exclaimed againſt in his time? doth not the ſame Prophet ſay truly of them, v.</hi> 5. <hi>hee that putteth not into their mouthes,</hi> they even prepare War againſt him? do they not with the moſt proſtitute Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings cry out, <hi>No penny, no Pater noſter?</hi> Is not maintenance, mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the burthen of all their Parlour or Pulpit paſtime? and why ſhould they ſo ſacrilegiouſly ſet a price on that which is but ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, the phancie of their owne braines, the reall truth whereof God required all true Diſciples to give for nothing? <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.8. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 55.1.2. or why ſhould people bee forced to buy the chaffer of theſe Clergy-merchants, rather then the wares or labour of a Shoomaker or porter? would not ſuch dealing be damned for an unjuſt monopoly, which yet theſe Encroachers practiſe without a Patent, if any but themſelves ſhould doe the like? Nay, why muſt we be forced to pay theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Clergymen for ſuch counterfeit ſervice and miniſtration which others will diſcharge better, and that for nothing? Is not this the greateſt infringing of the Subjects propriety which the Kingdome ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers? I ſay not this to undervalue the Miniſtery of the Goſpell, or to diſwade an ample and abundant maintenance to ſuch as truly labour in Gods Vineyard; but to exaggerate the heynouſneſſe of thoſe that doe not only ſet, as they pretend, the ineſtimable treaſure of the Goſpell, the unvaluable Word of God to ſale as if it were an unholy thing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. but as much as in them lyes, compell all people and Nations by fire and ſword to buy traſh and trumpery in ſtead thereof, and that at what price they themſelves pleaſe.</p>
            <p>I know this Controverſie will not eaſily be reconciled; our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Belly-Prieſts will doubtleſſe ſtruggle for their tythes, with no leſſe ſubtillity and ſtoutneſſe, than the Popiſh did, for their Supremacy and Peter-pence when the Reformation firſt began; the truth is, they ſtill plead preſcription for them in <hi>England,</hi> though they were long ſince damned by all Reformed Churches of <hi>Scotland, Sweadland, Denmarke, France, Germany,</hi> the <hi>Cantones,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> not without the inceſſant witneſſing againſt of Gods people amongſt us ever ſince, as is evident in their owne and other mens writings upon Record; but bad
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113400:10"/>Lawes, as well as Oathes, are better broke then kept, fitter to be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led than continued: I wiſh therefore, amongſt ſuch other hard queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and arguments, as have been put to them formerly, in this behalfe, they would likewiſe take into conſideration theſe few Queries.</p>
            <p>What is the difference betwixt a Miniſters calling, and any other, whether Handicraft or Tradeſmans? wherein are they diſtinguiſhed? What is requiſite to make them both legitimate? Is there not an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Call, and an inward Call to either of them?</p>
            <p>Whether may it now adayes bee infallibly diſcerned that a Miniſter is truly called to preach unto a people, any otherwayes, than by the peoples calling of him?</p>
            <p>Whether ought a Miniſter once called and accepted of to preach unto a People or Pariſh, leave the ſaid Pariſh or People all his life time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any pretence whatſoever, without conſent of thoſe that firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him?</p>
            <p>Whether may a Miniſter be ſaid to be truly called, who is put upon a Pariſh, contrary to the wills and approbation of the whole or major part thereof, as is the condition of moſt Pariſhes, according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Lawes of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether may ſuch a Miniſter as is once called to teach in any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, withdraw himſelfe without being called away by God that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him thither? How may a Miniſter know when God truly calls him from one Pariſh to another? Whether is it not moſt probable that ſuch are not called by God, but run away, who remove from a leane Benefice or Lecture unto a fat one?</p>
            <p>Whether did God ever really call any man to the Miniſtery of the Goſpell, without enduing him with gifts fit for ſuch a Calling? What are the neceſſary ſignes, gifts, and qualifications of ſuch a Calling?</p>
            <p>Whether is it not one neceſſary qualification of a Miniſter truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>divide the word of truth aright,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.15. <hi>to hold faſt the faithfull word as it hath been taught, and be able by ſound doctrine, both to exhort and to convince the gainſayers?</hi> Tit. 1.9.</p>
            <p>Whether have the <hi>Papiſt, Lutheran, Calviniſt, or Anabaptict, Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> or <hi>Independent,</hi> (any one, or either of them more then the other) any infallible way of exhorting and convincing gainſayers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Pauls</hi> rule to <hi>Titus?</hi> if they have, why doe they not ſhew it unto their brethren? If they have not, is it not a ſigne they are no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113400:11"/>true Miniſters, no true Chriſtians, that doe not beare with their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren untill they can convince them?</p>
            <p>If it be not in the Clergies power to make it infallibly appeare unto me, that ſuch a one is a Miniſter unto me, my Miniſter, after a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, nor any other manner, than ſuch a one, the very ſame, by which a man is, or becomes a Servingman unto me, my Servingman, to wit, becauſe I have accepted of, and entertained him into my ſervice; with what reaſon may this Miniſter require the tithes of my eſtate, whether I will or no, when this Servingman can recover nothing, but what I my ſelfe will give him or agree for with him? what reaſon can bee given why every man (if a pretended Miniſter will be ſo ſhameleſſe to put him to it) ſhould not capitulate and article with a Miniſter for his paines, his ſervice, as well as with a Servingman, a Porter? Why may not a Carpenter or Tayler be put upon every Pariſh, whether the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh will or no, as well as a Miniſter; and each of them pretend to doe the worke of the whole Pariſh in generall, and of every one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, compelling them to pay him for it, though he did no worke for them, through their default, as well as the Miniſter?</p>
            <p>But that I may be the better induc'd to render all reverence and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dues, which theſe Clergymen lay claime to, 'tis neceſſary that I be a little farther ſatisfied concerning the demonſtrative verity of ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary a Calling, as they pretend to be inveſted with, or how they have any preheminence above all other beleevers, who joyntly ſo long ſince were by <hi>Peter</hi> declared to be a <hi>royall Prieſthood,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p>For all that I can underſtand, theſe Clergymen were borne ſtarke naked as well as others; their education at Schools and Univerſity (to ſay no more) is no better then their fellows, and, in briefe, they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little to be diſtinguiſhed from other men, untill they begin to feel an itching, a longing after Tith-crops, by which (for all that can be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned) they judge themſelves to be ripe, and expect only Gods call unto the Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>That far, (I meane till they grow tith-ſicke) their progreſſe is not difficult, the world can apprehend it at well as they themſelves; but now forſooth, the reale of Gods houſe devours them daily, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69.9. and all ſuch as may be friend them, muſt know they have no reſt in ſpirit, through their vehement deſire that God would call them to preach the Goſpell Hereupon good people, like enough, enquire and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t about both lowne and Country, for ſome vacant Parſonage or Lectureſhip;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113400:11"/>ſuddenly one brings newes of 10.20.30.40. or 50. pounds worth of tithes, or other benevolences, which may be compaſſed, if God ſo pleaſe, (this phraſe mult in, that God may beare the blame, untill this new Evangeliſt be pleaſed;) hee gives them a gracious hearing and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, but finding it too ſmall, inferiour to his ravenous appetite, he ſtill with <hi>Moſes</hi> alleadges, that the Lord hath not yet appeared to him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.1. Hee doth not apprehend himſelfe to be ſufficiently called; and thus in the beſt ſeeming manner he can, he devours, untill ſome great Cedar falls to warme him by, untill the ſtalled Oxe bee killed to feaſt him with, untill a far Parſonage of 100, 200. or 300. pounds a year grow void, which no ſooner happens, but the firſt toal thereof pierces both his ears, that they ſtand liſtning continually, untill his Scoutes, ſome friend or other propound it to him, which is no ſooner mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but as if he were impatient, that his Predeceſſor had injured him to dye no ſooner, he breaks out with <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Speake Lord, for thy ſervant heareth,</hi> 1 Sam. 3.10. in briefe, their rule is, God calls them not to ſmall games, they are conſident he will not doe them ſo much injury, he will not have them ſerve him for nothing, much like to what the Devill ſaid of <hi>Job.</hi> c. 1.9, 10, 11. but if a fat Benefice be mentioned, they runne in full aſſurance that their God (God <hi>Mammon</hi>) calls them.</p>
            <p>Dear Reader, is this the truth? then ponder on it, and weigh well the conſequence thereof; let not thy underſtanding bee any longer captivated; be not ſuperſtitious, and thou ſhalt ſee greater things then theſe, <hi>Job.</hi> 1.50.</p>
            <p>Caſt then thy thoughts a little on all ſuch as pretend unto the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery among us; conſider their different wayes and doctrines, and thou ſhalt finde many of them to agree no leſſe then oppoſites, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions.</p>
            <p>Some of them hold the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a true, though erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and corrupted Church; others, that whoſoever lives and dyes in the beliefe thereof, cannot poſſibly attaine ſalvation. Some hold the Miniſtery in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a falſe Miniſtery, not knowing otherwiſe how to excuſe their ſeparation from it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Others dare not do ſo (no more then of their Baptiſme) as knowing their owne Miniſtery to be derived ſucceſſively from that of <hi>Rome.</hi> Some hold Epiſcopacy to be of Divine right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Others ſay as much for Presbytery; and not a few there be who affirm no peculiar government at all to be by Divine right. Some hold we are ſaved by faith alone: Others by ſuch not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113400:12"/>without good workes. Some hold that Chriſt could not bee juſt and equall, unleſſe he had dyed for all the world alike, even all that would believe on him: Others thinke Chriſt might poſſibly have loft his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, had he not dyed for a ſet number only, for his Elect, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot ſinne at all, or poſſibly miſcarry though they ſinne never ſo much. Some hold we are juſtified by Chriſts paſſive obedience only, and that for all his active obedience; he might have ſaid, hee was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable as touching mans redemption: Others affirme that not only Chriſts paſſive obedience, but his active alſo, were both neceſſary to our juſtification and his owne. To bee briefe, (for volumnes of this nature may recounted.) Some hold the baptizing of Infants to be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory: Others beleeve it may as well, if not better be diſpenced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Now, there are I ſay, in the Church of England men that teach all theſe contradictory doctrines, who yet pretend to have had an expreſſe calling unto the Miniſtery from God, extraordinary in reſpect to their Lay-brethren: They all ſtile themſelves Gods Ambaſſadours to us, they tell us that Chriſts words in <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. are as clearly to be underſtood of them and their ſucceſſours in their reſpective generations, as of the 70. Diſciples themſelves; to wit, <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me, and he that deſpiſeth you deſpiſeth me; and he that deſpiſeth me deſpiſeth him that ſout me:</hi> Thus doth each of them inculcate the <hi>Divinity</hi> both of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery and Doctrine upon the people, becauſe it <hi>brings in their tithes, their maintenance,</hi> with ſuch execrable threatnings, to thoſe that will not receive them, that they poore ſoules, having their judgements ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacled by ſuperſtitious feares, cannot chooſe but ſwallow them down unchew'd, untaſted.</p>
            <p>But ſince their Doctrines doe appeare ſo contradictory to ſuch as are not hood wink'd; ſince no one of them can prove his Miniſtery to be truer than the others; nay, ſince it is agreed on amongſt themſelves that their Miniſtery is one and the ſame, wee cannot with any ſhew of reaſon be required to beleeve them otherwiſe, than all alike, that is, ſo far forth only <hi>as we can be fully perſwaded thereof in our owns hearts,</hi> Rom. 14.5. which upon the very firſt reflection muſt needs conclude, that, <hi>ſince the callings and doctrines of them all canned poſſibly be ſound, implying contradictions; ſo cannot the calling of either of them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true, becauſe they all have the ſelfe ſame calling; as is evident by their come confeſſion and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to be brief, Tithes, as I have prov'd, were not doe until the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113400:12"/>came into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and that unto a Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> for parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular expreſſe purpoſes to wit, beſides others, that they ſhould give one tenth thereof for a heave offering unto the High Prieſt, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.27, 28, 29. who was to ſacrifice in the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the ſaid Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> was to attend and doe the ſervice of the Tabernacle, <hi>Num.</hi> 3.7, 8. and was only requlred to receive tithes of their brethren the <hi>Jewes,</hi> the other eleven Tribes which came out of the loynes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Heb. 5.7. and neither they the ſaid Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> nor the High Prieſt to have any other portion or inheritance beſides the tithes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18 20.23.24. from whence amongſt others, we may draw theſe few obſervations.</p>
            <p>1. According to the <hi>Leviticall law,</hi> the tithes <hi>of the land of Canaan only</hi> were payable, and that <hi>in the land of Canaan only,</hi> and <hi>from the Jewes their brethren only;</hi> But theſe pretended Tithmongers lay claime to the tithes of all the world, from all ſorts of Nations, to be due unto themſelves the Clergy.</p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Jewiſh Levites</hi> were a peculiar Tribe, upon whom the tithes were entailed from one generation to another, and by a Statute to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for ever, they were to have no other inheritance, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.23. but were to rely upon the Lord, who promiſed to be their portion: But theſe, who are no more of <hi>Levi</hi> his kindred than the <hi>Great Turke,</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto their wayes, not much unlike the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> or rather <hi>Romulus,</hi> ſuch of all Nations who are fitteſt for their turnes, by tricks and ſhifts, ſeducing whom they can, through a pretence of ſuperſtitious zeale, lay claime, rob, and run away with the fifth part of all their neighbours goods, wherein, notwithſtanding, they have ſo little truſt, and leſſe confidence in Gods promiſe, which was to be a portion unto the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiſh Levites,</hi> in whom there was no guile, that they lay up, hoard and purchaſe, as if they knew their poſterity were baſtards, and not to bee provided for, neither by tithes, nor Gods providence: And</p>
            <p>3. Whereas the true <hi>Levites</hi> were to give for a heave-offering unto the High Prieſt of the family of <hi>Aaron,</hi> one tenth of all their tithes, our <hi>Engliſh Levites</hi> ſince their High Prieſt and head the Pope was baniſhed out of <hi>England,</hi> pretend to pay (when they cannot avoid it, for they are ſlow enough in payments) unto the King: I know not what firſt buits inſtead thereof, and indeed they made him ſo far forth their High Prieſt to beare their iniquities, that what ever they have of late beene queſtioned for, they caſt upon his back.</p>
            <p>I know the common ſcarcrow and objection which it made againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113400:13"/>an unſetled maintenance, to wit, that moſt men are ſo backward to all good duties, eſpecially in matter of expence, that if they be not both rated and compelled to pay, they will not pay at all, or not their ſhares proportionably; and that if there be not both a certain &amp; a round allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſuch as have hitherto applyed themſelves to ſtudy for ſervice of the Church, will grow diſcouraged, betake themſelves to other callings, and by this meanes the Goſpell become contemptible, through want of an able and learned Miniſtery: To this I anſwer, that it is evident by experience that ſuch Miniſters of the Congregationall way as have good parts, and are conſcionable in their callings, although they leave every one of their Congregation to contribute as God has enabled them according to the purpoſe of their owne hearts, not grudgingly, which was <hi>Pauls</hi> rule, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. I ſay, that ſuch have a maintenance equall (if not exceeding) to what the tithes produced in the Biſhops times, or may doe againe hereafter if they were to be continued. Secondly, for ſuch as will not put themſelves to ſtudy for the Churches ſervice, unleſſe they be encouraged by maintenance; I ſay, they are guilty of a ſinne ſurpaſſing <hi>ſymony,</hi> a nameleſſe ſinne, a ſinne ſo infamous, as none were found in the Goſpel-time ſo vile and deſperate to commit it, and give occaſion unto a law at once expreſſely both to name it and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne it; <hi>Simon Magus</hi> his ſin was not ſo great as theirs, hee would have bought the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, theſe men would ſell them if they had them; <hi>Simon Magus</hi> thought ſo well of the Holy Ghoſt, that he would have purchaſed it with money, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.18, 19. But theſe ſons of covetouſneſſe are ſo baſely ſordid, that they will not accept of it <hi>gratis,</hi> unleſſe they may, at ſame time, have a Grant, a Monopoly to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the counterfeit gifts thereof upon the people, at an enhanced, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne exciſed rate. Thirdly, ſuch men doe plainly by their practiſe declare to all the world, that there is no difference between the calling of ſuch hackney Miniſters, and the calling of a Merchant, Cobler, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Handicraftſman, but that it is indifferent, and all alike, free for every one to betake himſelfe to which of them he pleaſes, and thinkes will prove moſt gainſome and beneficiall to him: And laſtly, if tythes bee the Clergies due by Divine right, as is determitted by that great Caſuiſt of the Aſſembly, Dr. <hi>Burges,</hi> with ſundry others of the ſame ſoul; then are all the Lay-men of <hi>England</hi> highly guilty of ſacriledge, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them by Impropriations: but if by a meere humane, a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary-law, only they lay claime unto them, then may it the better be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113400:13"/>ſince it ſo much intrenches upon the ſubjects propriety in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and upon the moſt tender conſciences of many in particular.</p>
            <p>And when they are admoniſhed to labour with their hands from <hi>Pauls</hi> example, rather then be chargeable unto the people, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. they anſwer, that though <hi>Paul</hi> did labour, yet it was of his owne good will and curteſie, there was no obligation for it, and ſeeke to prove it by thoſe words of <hi>Pauls,</hi> where he ſayes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. have not <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> a power, as well as the other Apoſtles, to forbeare wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king? to which I reply, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had the ſame power to forbeare working, which the brethren had to forbeare giving them maintenance, the one could not be compelled to worke, neither might the other be forced to ſet meat and drinke before them, or any others, much leſſe if they were perſons addicted unto idleneſſe.</p>
            <p>But I preſume it will not be pleaded in <hi>Pauls</hi> behalfe, that he or any body elſe might lawfully paſſe their time in idleneſſe, eſpecially ſince we finde that <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſſe command unto the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> was, that <hi>if any would not worke, he ſhould not eat,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3.10. So neither is it pretended that Chriſtians may lawfully refuſe adminiſtring to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of their brethren, eſpecially, of ſuch as teach them ſpirituall things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Paul</hi> cannot be ſaid to require any other power of forbearing to worke, than what the other Apoſtles had, or made uſe of, and we may not imagine of them, that they were idly given; doubtleſſe they omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no opportunity of imploying their time, as might be moſt advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and edifying unto the brethren, and upon this ſuppoſition they were to ſpend the whole day, even all their dayes, between providing for their owne livelihood, their health, and the propagation of the Goſpell; now, beſides modetate recreation, meat and drinke was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for keeping them alive, which they muſt have got by labouring with their owne hands, or elſe have beene ſupplyed therewith from the brethren, if the brethren did ſupply <hi>Paul,</hi> with food and rayment, then might he have forborne to worke, as he inſinuates, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. but then he muſt have ſpent ſo much more time with labouring in the word and doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. for he muſt not have beene idle, as was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid before, but by <hi>Pault</hi> practice 'tis evident he might not forbeare wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, when his receiving maintenance, would have proved chargeable to the brethren.</p>
            <p>But to conclude; Our Saviour it exacting of the Goſpel-Miniſtery,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113400:14"/>leſt his Diſciples, being ignorant how to demeane themſelves, ſhould goe about to carve their owne maintenance, when hee firſt ſent them out to preach the Goſpell, he charges them expreſſely, ſaying, <hi>freely yet have received, freely give,</hi> Matth. 10.8. then, that they might not reſt any wayes perplexed through feare of want, as ſuch who might appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend themſelves altogether unprovided of neceſſaries, he bids them <hi>cat ſuch things as were ſet before them,</hi> Luke 10.8. and that they, and their ſucceſſors in the Miniſtery of the Goſpell, might be the better induced to relye upon the ſame providence ever after, being returned from their Miniſtery, he askes them, ſaying, <hi>When I ſent you without purſe and ſcrip, and ſhooes, wanted ye any thing, and they ſaid, We wanted nothing,</hi> Luke 22.35. whereunto I will only adde, that for thoſe who now tearme themſelves Miniſters, and will not be contented with ſuch wages and maintenance as Chriſt appointed them, it is more then ſuſpicious that they have no ſnare nor portion, neither in the Apoſtles faith, Miniſtery nor Goſpell.</p>
            <p>After I had finiſhed this ſhort Diſcourſe, there came unto my hands Mr. <hi>Seldens Hiſtory of Tythes,</hi> which I muſt needs ſay, I had not ſeene before, and am confident it will not be ungratefull unto the Reader, if I here preſent him with ſome Quotations which I bring from thence, and what I have obſerved, as a briefe abſtract of the Hiſtory it ſelf.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quotations.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter Damian</hi> complaines of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 2. about 10 60. that Infeodations or conveyances of perpetuall right of tither were granted to Lay-men. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>ep.</hi> 12. <hi>apud Seld. c.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leutardes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Rodol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ben Hiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wickleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> aſſerted that tithes were m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> almes, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> might <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> which was condemned by the Councell of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Infeo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tions of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, ſuch as were made unto Lay, men before the Canon <hi>Prohibemus</hi> of the Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> held under <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>80, are to this day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113400:14"/>other Lay-inheritances, although none can now be created in <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Selden Hiſt. c.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>The Canon law of the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church never commanded any thing concerning tithes. <hi>Id. c.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodore Balſamen</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Antioch</hi> adviſes <hi>Mark</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> touching the quantity of what was to be offered in the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Churches, that no certaine quantity is appointed by the Canons, and that through the inequality of mens eſtates (none of them giving any ſuch part to the Church as that it could diſcover their abilities) which permits not a regular certainty, they were contented with what cuſtome, and free bounty of the givers beſtowed. <hi>Reſponſ.</hi> 57. <hi>inter monumenta Juris Graeco Romani.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> in his anſwer to <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monke, tells him, that the cuſtome is generally to make a quadripartite diviſion of all Church offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, or tithes; for the Biſhop, for his Clergy, for the poore, and for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Churches; but admoniſhes him that in tenderneſſe of the <hi>Engliſh-Saxon</hi> Church, he and his Clergy ſhould ſtill imitate the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of all things uſed in the Primitive times under the Apoſtles.</hi> Selden of Tithes. c. 9.</p>
               <p>Diſſerences about Tithes were decided by the Sheriffes and Biſhops in the <hi>Saxons</hi> times, and afterwards made determinable in the Biſhops Conſiſtory by <hi>William the Conqueror.</hi> Id. c. 14. ſect. 1. &amp; ſeq.</p>
               <p>Temporall Courts did notwithſtanding judge of tithes even untill <hi>Henry</hi> theſe conds time, and in certain caſes and manner of proceedings till <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds time. <hi>Id. Ibid.</hi> ſect. 4.5.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtance</hi> in <hi>Cyprus</hi> about the yeare 380. wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt certaine heretickes of the Primitive times, ſpeaking of the <hi>Teſſareſderatitae,</hi> or thoſe which thought that <hi>Eaſter</hi> muſt needs be kept on the 14. Moone according to the Law given the <hi>Jewes.</hi> concerning the Paſſeover, fearing that obſerving of it otherwiſe might ſubject them to the curſe of the law, ſayes, they might as well be lyable to the ſame curſe, for not circumciſing, for not paying tithes, for not offering at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> which is an undeniable argument that in thoſe dayes, and in thoſe parts, they paid no tithes, no more then they did ſacrifice, or circumciſe, <hi>Id. Revew.</hi> of <hi>Ch.</hi> 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113400:15"/>
               <head>Obſervations.</head>
               <p>THe Councells for the firſt 600. yeares take no notice of tithes, but of offerings and lands poſſeſſed with their Revenues.</p>
               <p>All that was received in the Biſhopricke or Pariſh (for both words had but one ſignification at firſt) by ſuch as were appointed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, was divided into foure parts, whereof one fourth was for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Miniſtery, out of which every Curate had his monthly ſalary; one fourth to reliefe of the poor, ſicke and ſtrangers; one fourth to reparation of Churches, and one fourth to the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe or Pariſh; but this courſe was proper to the Dioceſſe of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Untill the yeare 800. Lay-men who were Patrons of Churches, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with their Chaplins, and ſuch Incumbents as they put in of all ſuch offerings as were made, as appeares by Councells, and Imperiall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulaties.</p>
               <p>Towards the end of the 400. yeare, ſome few devouter people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to pay tithes, or rather duties, no proportion being eſtabliſhed, for reliefe of the poore, which continued chiefly, if not only for their uſe, untill about the end of the 800. yeare, at which time they began to be devoted unto Churches, at the ſole diſpoſition of the Clergy, not the Parſon only, but of ſome fraternity of Monkes, at the Benefactors choice, yet ſo that the Doner might appropriate them to what Church he pleaſed, though it were ſituate in an other Pariſh, or precinct, then where the tithes were to be gathered. That of <hi>Lateran</hi> was the firſt Generall Councell which mentioned tithes about the yeare 1130. and no Canon commanded the payment of tithes, till the <hi>Lateran</hi> Generall Councell in the yeare. 1215.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:113400:15"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
